Guide to the Taylor Family Papers, 1850-1975 RL.01277
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Taylor family papers
1850-1975 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Taylor family
RL.01277
3.0 Linear Feet
Missionaries to Nigeria for the Southern Baptist Foreign Missions Board, 1955-1962. Family letters, photographs, and diaries from the Taylor family's mission work in Nigeria and their return voyage to the United States. Also includes a selection of photocopied letters from T. J. Bowen to James A. Taylor, 1850-1867, documenting Bowen's life as a missionary to Africa.
1000 Items
Access Restrictions
Access restricted: Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of listening copies.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Taylor Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013 and 2014.
Biographical Note
Duke alumnus Orville Walters "Tom" Taylor (Ph.D., 1956) and his wife, Evelyn Taylor, went as missionary teachers to Nigeria with their son Michael in 1955. While there the Taylors had three daughters: Priscilla, Melissa, and Penelope. The family returned to the United States in 1962.
Nigeria -- Social life and customs; Nigeria -- Description and travel; Married people in missionary work; Children of missionaries; Missionaries -- Nigeria; Southern Baptist Convention. Foreign Mission Board; Taylor, Evelyn Adella Bonham; Taylor, Orville Walters; Taylor family; Taylor family
- Papers, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Family letters, photographs, and diaries from the Taylor family's mission trip to Nigeria and their return voyage to the United States. Also includes a selection of photocopied letters from T. J. Bowen to James A. Taylor, 1850-1867, documenting Bowen's life as a missionary to Africa.
  - Collection and genealogical information (Box 1)
  - Evelyn Taylor's diary, 1954-1962 (Box 1)
    From appointment to the Mission Board through the first years in Nigeria.
  - "My Life," by O.W. Taylor, 1955 (Box 1)
    Autobiography written as part of Taylor's application for the Foreign Missions Board.
  - Programs, schedules, and bulletins from the Nigerian mission, 1957-1978 (Box 1)
    Includes Newton School programs, finances, political and public events in Iwo, and other memorabilia from the Taylors' work and school.
  - Newton News newsletters, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between Michael Taylor and his parents, 1955-1960 (Box 1)
    Written from his time boarding at the Newton Memorial School.
  - Correspondence between Evelyn Taylor and her family in the United States, 1955-1962 (Box 1)
  - Itineraries and diary from the family's trip home, 1962 (Box 1)
  - O.W. Taylor's Encyclopedia of Southern History contributions re: Duke University, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Photographs from Nigeria, 1950s-1960s (Box 1)
  - Photographs from the Nigerian Baptist Missionaries reunion, undated (Box 1)
  - Taylor family photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from T.J. Bowen to Rev. James B. Taylor, 1850-1867 (photocopies) (Box 1)
    Includes details on Bowen's missionary work in Africa and South America, his family's health, and some discussion of the Civil War. Collected by O.W. Taylor for a research project.
  - Application for Missionary Service: Evelyn Taylor, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Article for West African Journal of Education, 1962 March (Box 2)
  - Untitled Notes, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Baptist Atlas, by Albert Wardin, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Nigerian Baptist Proceedings, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Missionary Album and Foreign Missions Directory, 1954-1995 (Box 2)
  - O.W. Taylor's Bible in Nigeria and at Duke, 1960-1962 (Box 2)
  - The Story of Sacred Wood Carvings, From One Small Yoruba Town, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Yoruba Bible, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Yoruba Bible, 1958 (Box 2)
  - ODU: A Journal of Yoruba and Related Studies (No. 7), 1959 (Box 2)
  - Fentola: A Little Girl of Africa, by Margaret Marchman, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Nigerian Baptist Mission 1961 Minutes (Box 2)
  - Foreign Mission Week Programme, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Manuals for Missionaries, 1954 and 1957 (Box 2)
  - Taiwo Ati Kehinde, by Iwe Keji, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Tales from Ire, by Barbara Epperson, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Bible Presented to O.W & Evelyn Taylor upon leaving Nigeria (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Cambridge Bible
  - Christianity in West Africa: The Nigerian Story, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Dictionary of the Yoruba Language (Box 2)
  - A History of Indigenous Labour on the Nigerian Railway, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Yoruba Language and Grammar Book (Box 3)
  - Cloth Commemorating 150th Anniversary of Baptist Work in Nigeria (Box 3)
    Two pieces of cloth
  - Duro Ladipo's Oba Koso: Dance-Drama with Yoruba Festival Music (2 disc set), 1975 (Audio-phonodisc LP 1)
  - The African Mbira: Music of the Shona People of Rhodesia, 1971 (Audio-phonodisc LP 2)